so today I'm going to talk about the
number one danger of prolong fasting
okay and that danger would be this you
die okay I mean unfortunately you can't
fast forever right at some point you're
going to run out of fat Fuel and you're
going to run out of uh muscle and organ
fuel because that is what happens after
you do fasting it turns into starvation
once the muscles are being consumed for
calories and then there'll be a point
where you just die however that's not
going to happen to you because I'm going
to show you exactly how to do this
because on the flip side there's no
other action that you can do to create
more Health than prolong fasting so I'm
going to show you how to do this safely
a couple other problems with fasting
that people run into is that um they may
lose some muscle okay or they may create
nutritional deficiencies because the
purpose of eating is to not just get
fuel but to also supply all your
nutrients however that's a really simple
problem to overcome if you know what
nutrients to take but in this video I
want to talk more about uh protein and
specifically muscle protein how to
prevent the loss of your muscle while
you do prolonged fasting the question is
how do we get the benefits of improved
immune system or getting rid of cancer
if we have cancer or strengthening our
brain getting more cognitive function
and elevated mood improvements and
getting rid of inflammatory conditions
and degenerative uh conditions as well
as extending our life and how do we do
all that and retain our muscle protein
now the first thing you need to know is
that the fatter you are the longer you
have the ability to eat yourself and I'm
talking about eating up your fat your
reserves when you're doing prolonged
fasting you are living off your body
tissue specifically adapost tissue and
the more of that you have the longer you
can fast without any problems
unfortunately especially with people
that have cancer that really want to do
prolonged fasting for like 20 days or
even 30 days if they don't have enough
fat it becomes very difficult however
I'm going to show you what I'm going to
recommend and today we're just going to
answer a lot of questions one question
I'm just going to handle right from the
very beginning is can you gain muscle
while you're doing fasting fasting is
not the best strategy for building up
your muscle mass okay chances are you're
not going to build too much muscle when
you're fasting even no growth hormone is
going way up because muscle growth is a
reflection of more calories as well as
exercise and so if you're eating no
calories it's going to be very difficult
to increase muscle mass however um I'm
more interested in preserving muscle
mass okay and a couple things you need
to know about preserving your muscle
number one the more you you are into
ketosis the less muscle you're going to
break down so ketones prevent the
breakdown of muscle tissue that's one
thing the other thing that happens when
you do fasting is you really Spike
growth hormone and growth hormone also
spares your muscle okay prevents the
loss of muscle muscle preservation is a
Survival action so your body wants to
preserve muscle so it will go after
other things first and so this is a
perfect Bridge to this topic of
autophagy autophagy is a condition in
your body where your body is recycling
old damaged proteins throughout the body
okay your muscle is not just protein in
fact every single cell in your body
contains some protein you have skin
intestines fascia connective tissue all
of that is protein and when you do
prolong fasting you trigger autophagy
and so you're getting this recycling of
this damaged protein into new amino
acids so there's a lot of benefits for
mitophagy and one being getting rid of
uh pathogens so if you have viruses in
your body that are just kind of
lingering around your body will take
care of those and get rid of those and
so people have a concern about their
muscles uh being eaten up from autophagy
but you have to realize that like I said
before all cells are made from protein
skin intestines
and so your muscles actually are going
to be dining off of your skin cells and
intestine cells the damaged skin cells
the damaged connective tissue cells
maybe scar tissue that you had or all of
this damaged protein will be fed to your
muscle before your muscle gives up its
amino acids which is a really cool thing
now as long as you have enough fat your
body is not going to tap into the muscle
reserve of any significant amount this
video is not really about intermittent
fasting this is about prolonged fasting
so you're fasting uh three days 5 days
seven days two weeks a month okay the
question is how do we make sure that we
preserve a muscle especially if you are
going into this prolonged fasting with
atrophy okay let's say you're menopausal
and some of your muscles are atrophied
okay which looks very very similar to
fat and you start doing long-term
fasting how do you deal with that
because some of that muscle is also
damaged now this is what I recommend
autophagy is inhibited by eating and
eating protein especially okay but it
goes on like a gradient type thing right
so when you start eating less than a
thousand calories a day you'll start
triggering autophagy to a certain degree
and the less that you eat the more tagy
you're going to trigger so it really has
to do with quantity or amounts of
calories and so you can induce autophagy
or get the benefits uh even doing a low
calorie type diet it's called calorie
restriction okay you can do that but of
course you're going to get a little bit
more benefits if you're doing just
straight fasting with no calories for
the first two or three days okay 48 to
72 hours I'm going to recommend not
taking any type of uh protein or amino
acid supplements however
at the fourth day of fasting you
introduce amino acids and here's why
amino acids are the building blocks of
protein and so by taking straight amino
acids it gives your body this already
broken down building block that your
tissues can start to use immediately
your liver doesn't have to work to break
it down and when you take amino acids
there's very little calories okay but
when you start the prolonged fasting if
you allow the body to clean up a lot of
the old damaged proteins then add the
amino acids let's say the fourth day and
then you start taking amino acids after
that you are consuming something that's
very low calorie your muscles can then
utilize these amino acids and the other
tissues can utilize these amino acids uh
to prevent fatigue and to prevent any
type of loss of any protein tissue from
there on out and at the same time get
all these wonderful benefits the type of
amino acid blend that I'm going to
recommend I put a link down below
because this specific blend has been
proven to be very effective and it does
not turn into sugar like a lot of other
um collagen type products or protein
products do so in other words you want
to use an amino acid blend that is very
very balanced the next question is uh
should you exercise or not well um this
all depends again on how much fat that
you have as your reserve and also so it
depends on how adapted you are to fat
when you start ketosis and you're new to
it you can be in ketosis within two or
three days okay but to be really fat
adapted that takes more like a month to
three months okay where you are just
burning fat like a machine when your
body is in that situation you can handle
a heavier workout a more intense workout
because when you work out you're going
to be tapping into fat not just sugar
reserves your glycogen and your muscle
and your liver in which you would run
out really quickly and then get really
tired so the more adapted you are the
more you're going to maintain your
energy while exercising and exercise as
itself is a very potent stimulus of
theophagy and so you'll get a lot more
benefits if you combine the exercise
with prolonged fasting but if you're not
fully adapted long walks should be
totally fine and something I would
recommend and then the next question is
supplements what type of supplements
should you be taking well this is the
list right here electrolytes okay
electrolyte powder make sure you have
electrolytes with enough potassium
because our bodies require a lot of it
uh the B vitamins are very very
important uh you may want to take
nutritional yeast unfortified because
that gives you the natural form of B
vitamins sea salt very important no less
than one teaspoon a day a lot of people
do not consume enough sea salt and
you're going to feel very weak when you
do this process especially your muscle
because of the sodium that's required
that go along with these other
electrolytes like potassium you might
want to take vitamin D uh better yet get
sun if you can if you can't take vitamin
D simply because even though it's a fat
cable vitamin so many people are
deficient in vitamin D going into it and
so fasting tends to aggravate this
deficiency the other thing I'm going to
recommend is omega-3 fatty acids a good
source would be civer oil um because
civer oil not only has omega-3
fatty acids but it also has vitamin d as
well as Vitamin A so you can actually
kill three birds with one stone I would
also recommend a natural source of
vitamin C and vitamin E if you're doing
like maybe a week of fasting or longer
just because um those are two other
vitamins like the water soluble vitamin
C that's going to go through your body
pretty quick and we don't want you to
start ending up with vitamin C
deficiencies as well as Vitamin E
deficiencies and this way you'll
maintain your strength you'll prevent
nutritional deficiencies you'll be able
to even exercise and you'll be able to
get the benefits of weight loss too and
look healthy as you lose weight as well
as all the internal benefits that are
occurring with this prolonged fast now
one last point about cancer if you have
cancer and you're doing this I would try
to go longer without taking the amino
acids simply because there are certain
amino acids that can feed the cancer so
if you do a straight fast without the
amino acids I think you'll benefit
greatly unless you have certain symptoms
like significant muscle loss things like
that but overall I would rather lose
more weight and be very very skinny and
get rid of the cancer than be focused on
you know preventing that weight loss and
end up dying from cancer prolong fasting
is hands down the best strategy of
getting rid of cancer if you have cancer
even if it's stage four I've done videos
on this so realize that any negative
effects from fasting don't even come
close to the benefits of doing fasting
for cancer now I have another video on
the details of how to do prolong fasting
and what to eat after you stop fasting
and check it out I put it up right here